<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>Wamsicks</title>
    <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk</link>
    <description>Wamsicks Blog Posts</description>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 10:06:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <ttl>1721901998</ttl>
    <image>
        <url>https://www.wamsicks.uk/favicon.png</url>
        <title>Wamsicks</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk</link>
    </image>
    <atom:link href="https://www.wamsicks.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <icon>
        <url>https://www.wamsicks.uk/favicon16.ico</url>
        <size>16x16</size>
    </icon>
    <icon>
        <url>https://www.wamsicks.uk/favicon32.ico</url>
        <size>32x32</size>
    </icon>
    <icon>
        <url>https://www.wamsicks.uk/favicon48.ico</url>
        <size>48x48</size>
    </icon>
    
    <item>
        <title>A Punch</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/a_punch.html</link>
        <description>
        <h1>A Punch</h1>
        <h3>Returning to the scene of the crime</h3>
	    <h3>First published: 15th June 2020</h3>
        <p>I want to talk about that thing. Yeah, THAT THING. I’m sure you are aware (if you know me that is) that last year at around this time, I was assaulted. Long story short, I was walking to catch a bus after getting off the train, a guy came after me swearing and telling me that I nudged him (not that I had noticed). He proceeded to push me, then try to trip me, then punched me from behind (because he was a coward, obviously). My jaw was broken, on the right side of my face (my left) the mandible was totally broken into two pieces, at my chin the mandible was fractured. After a pretty terrible time of dealing with A&amp;E under the Tories, which consisted of waiting four hours before being seen whilst I was spitting or swallowing massive amounts of my own blood, stayed with my parents and they took me to a hospital about an hour and a half away for me to have surgery. It was a great success; I have to say. One colleague even remarked that I looked as handsome as ever! Three major issues have crept up in my mind arising from this event: my interaction with the police, my mental health and my view and perception of other people.</p>
        <p>I wasn’t the one to go to the police, my parents were, and the police were slow to get around to actually interviewing me. In fact, it was almost two weeks until they finally got around to it. When they finally did, I was asked the question “what do you hope to get from this”? At that moment, I knew where I stood. I told him that I wanted the person to be identified so that it could be stopped from happening again. Inside, all my instincts were being justified: I thought it would be a waste of time to involve the police as nothing good would come of it. In fact, I would have to ring up to get CCTV footage from the bus company just so there was some footage of the person who did it. I never heard back about it and I never expect to.</p>
        <p>This didn’t help me to feel particularly good mentally. The aftermath of what had happened was actually an uptick in my emotions towards everything. I didn’t feel fear or an anger, I just wanted to get on with it and get back to things. During my time waiting for surgery and even immediately after coming around, I was chatting and joking with the nurses who were taking care of me. Maybe the fact that they had taken such good care of me and where willing to make me feel better helped with that. It wasn’t until a few weeks had passed and I was getting back to my normal routine that I realised that I wasn’t right mentally. There were a few times when I went to town with my then girlfriend and thought that I was being followed or that someone was trying to come for me or intimidate me. I was dealing with anxiety for the first time since school. I struggled to go out and do things as I normally would and my frustrations boiling over probably led to us breaking up. It was the breakup the finally pushed me to get help.</p>
        <p>Through the company’s EAP scheme, I was able to see a therapist and finally work through some of the things that had happened and deal with the stress and rage that had come about from it. She was fantastic and a great help. I opened up about my torrid past and even though I had been passed though because of what happened to me that year, we ended up dealing with a large range of things that I covered in a previous post. Looking at this as a continuum rather than separate events made me realise that I was dealing well with the situation I was dealt. When you are used to crisis, terrible things shock you less. I even told her that this wouldn’t make my top three worst things that have happened to me and she saw that although I was struggling, that coping strategies would help me to keep on going without having the breakdown that I may have been due.</p>
        <p>The problem is that I was still struggling to relate to a world that felt fundamentally different to the one that I had conceived of. Was it a contrived gaze or was the situation shaking my expectations of the way things are? I suppose both were true. I have always been idealistic, and this continues to be the case but now I have a more nuanced view of people that I did. When you believe that the world needs to be changed to be fundamentally fairer so that we can all benefit from a just society, the immediate impact of a fist breaking your jaw isn’t “well here’s some proof!” For a long time, I questioned whether people could be trusted at all. Luckily this didn’t last too long as I was able to see the contradictions in this logic of nihilism. The more pernicious problem was my relationships to people closer to me.</p>
        <p>Before surgery, I posted on Facebook about what had happened and about some of the great support I had received from many of my friends and colleagues. I received a flood of positive messages and many people messaged to see how I was getting on. After that initial flurry, came the people who would stick by me and lend a hand when I needed it. Except, that didn’t happen. A couple of friends came to see me and checked up on me but the vast majority who posted nice massages haven’t actually messaged me since. It’s almost like I had been forgotten. I don’t want to sound like I’m attacking anyone but after a few months without anyone checking in, I felt the way I did the last time something terrible happened, like I had been abandoned. I don’t know what else I was supposed to expect really, I haven’t built close relationships with anyone new for a long time, partly because the circumstances have meant that I don’t keep in touch or because I struggle mentally with interacting when I don’t see people very often. Perhaps I have idealised my (apparently) longer lasting friendships too much. Perhaps the sands of time laid waste to these relationships and I hadn’t seen it.</p>
        <p>What would have been nice though, is to have had an inkling that this might have been the case. It’s bewildering to realise that the people you have valorised no longer hold you in the same level of esteem. It’s dumbfounding to realise that you haven’t moved on when they have. It’s traumatic to think that perhaps it had always been this way.</p>
        <p>I meant to write this last year, but the last paragraph was too difficult to articulate until now. Especially in the context of knowing I have very limited outlets for expression and reciprocation, I have a couple of people who I can talk to and I am very grateful for that. I hope this doesn’t sound like hyperbole. I don’t want to cause friction and neither do I want to hurt anyone else, but the truth is that because I don’t value myself, I don’t have plans, I don’t have dreams and I don’t look to the future.</p>  
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 12:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/a_punch.html</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>What's it all about?</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/wiaa.html</link>
        <description>
        <h1>What’s it all about?</h1>
        <h3>I don't know, don't ask me</h3>
	    <h3>First published: 6th January 2020</h3>
        <p>Ontologically, I mean. For those who daren’t ask, that’s when you think about what it means to be. Usually, I like to divide myself from fantasy or at least put myself into fantasy that is so foreign or barren that it is too distinct from my reality to me confuse it. Unfortunately (or fortunately depending on your outlook), when something gets to you and really takes you along for the ride, the fantasy is inescapable.</p>
        <p>When you are presented with a depiction of an alternative reality, even if it is ghastly and morbid, it can sometimes force you to confront your reality and make you ask uncomfortable questions about it. Here I am, living a comfortable life, doing well enough, but the feeling constant nagging away at me is that there has to be something bigger and better out there to do, to be a part of. Good fantasy can fill you with excitement and dread and that is precisely what it did and it made me question whether or not I had experienced similar feelings recently. In all honesty, I cannot remember the last time I felt that kind of thrill. I am not writing this to say that live ought to be exciting and full of boundless fun, but I am saying that it need not be so mundane.</p>
        <p>I get the feeling that I am not the only person that feels this way and that this life is not the one that they wanted to have. I hear from some that this is the reality of what you deal with later in life. I hear from others that I should be more grateful for what I have. To have gratitude for salvation from scarcity is one thing, but I cannot bring myself to accept banality. Perhaps I am at fault for this as my choice to spurn the magic of inspiration on too many occasions could mean that I may well have run dry or, it may be that working has taken away vital time and energy from the divine impulse of creativity. Either way, it is remarkable that a couple of hours of someone else’s wonderous light has set the fire of my mind burning.</p>
        <p>I hope that this will return me to a better and fuller time, but I have my doubts. In the meantime, I will seize upon the opportunities that creativity gives to me when it sees fit.</p>
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/wiaa.html</guid>
    </item>

        <item>
        <title>Tears of Suburbia</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/suede1.html</link>
        <description>
        <h1>Tears of Suburbia</h1>
        <h3>A love letter to Suede</h3>
        <h3>First published: 27th April 2019</h3>
        <p>When I look back at some of the pivotal moments of my life, it seems weird to me that one of the most significant events that happened to me was going to YouTube and playing a song, but that is one of the idiosyncratic things about life, little moments can have profound consequences. I was very into heavy metal, grunge and punk before I turned 16 and after then I had started to listen to a much wider variety of music. At 17 and 18, I was particularly fond of British indie in the 80s and 90s; Britpop and shoegazing were mainstays on the playlist of the Creative Zen mp3 player I had at the time. Blur especially were a huge draw for me, I like the way that Damon Albarn looked, sang, the stuff he’d talked about and I particularly like what he said to Tony Blair when he was invited to hobnob with New Labour and their sycophants. I read up on him a little bit and learned about his relationship with Justine Frischmann. For some bizarre reason, when I heard that she was with another guy in a band called Suede before, I was a bit apprehensive about them and when I saw Brett Anderson’s face for the first time, I intensely disliked them.</p>
        <p>After breaking up with my then girlfriend, I was in a bad place and doing a fair bit of soul-searching. I was challenging a lot of the feelings that I had about life and myself in general, but I knew that I wasn’t going to find any real comfort in what surrounded me. Most of the people I had as friends had either gone to university or had deserted me for a variety of reasons and my family was less help because although they are great for practical and structural support, emotionally or psychologically I would not know where to start with them. I wanted to expand my horizons with music still and I kept seeing that Suede had been an influence on many of the bands that I liked at the time so I decided that this was the time to finally just bite the bullet and give them a listen.</p>
        <p>That first listen was surreal. I listened to the same song about 15 times in a row before moving on to the next one and the next one. Animal Nitrate to this day is the song that if hear it in passing, I have to stop and listen, if not sing along to. I went walking from my parent’s house in Chatham down to the charity shops in Rochester to look at the old CDs and LPs as I didn’t have much cash at the time. I ended up finding a Suede single, with a pig in a bright blue suit and a red tie on and bought it for 50p. I opened the case and found it was the Animal Nitrate single. As soon as I got home, I played it on repeat. Painted People became another one of my favourites and I loved the versatility they showed as a band to make something as great as The Big Time.</p>
        <p>In the next few months I bought their first four albums, I would have bought their fifth and final album (at the time) but I couldn’t seem to get it anywhere. I listened to their eponymous first, repeatedly and was in awe of what I was hearing, the drums and bass created a backdrop for Bernard Butler to unleash arpeggio after arpeggio into each track, he played with purpose, completely different to anyone else I’ve heard before or since. But it was the voice, and more importantly the words, of Brett Anderson that stuck me. His high pitched, half falsetto is not easy to imitate and immediately strikes you as beyond what most singers would sound like. The words shared a similarly abstract quality.</p>
        <p>The effect that Brett’s androgyny had on me was massive, the words often carried a sexual quality and whether or not the songs were about fucking or not, their always had a debase sensibility, as Bernard mentions about The Living Dead, “I've written this really beautiful piece of music and it's a squalid song about junkies.” It made me focus too on the false way in which so many things were put into black and white choices in life and that there is a way in which society designs the way that we have to interact with everything about each other and ourselves. In the most extreme case, it made me think a lot about gender. I wasn’t comfortable with the way that I perceived myself at the time, I was trying to play up to a masculine stereotype that has never really felt like me. That’s not to say I don’t have masculine traits, it’s just that there are many masculine traits that I haven’t internalised very well or that I actively despise. Equally, I feel I do have so feminine traits, which some people are only to happy to remind me of. Listening to these lyrics allowed me to be more comfortable about this and gave me the push to actually take these questions on directly.</p>
        <p>Moving away to London was a big change for me, it was the first time that I had really been away from family for an extended period. Strangely, I had listened to Suede, Coming Up and Head Music but not Dog Man Star at this point. Why? I honestly am still not sure but there was something in my brain that said don’t listen to it yet. I’m glad I waited. From September through to December 2010, I didn’t listen to much else and it was an almost religious experience. I am still a bit obsessed with the album now. It appeared heavily on the setlist when I saw them for the first time at the O2 that December. I just remember getting back that evening and thinking, I need to see them again. Sure enough, I bought tickets for the three gigs they were doing at the Brixton Academy in the coming May, one album a night for each of their first three albums. When it came around to it, I was buzzing. Standing in line, I couldn’t wait for it to start. A guy behind me in the line asked for a photo and we got talking about all sorts of stuff, music, sports, politics etc. Over the coming nights, I ended up chatting to him more and more. Eight years on, Dave and I are really good mates and he’s one of the few people that I can rely on.</p>
        <p>They have given me more than I really thought musicians ever could, and I haven’t even met them! So, for all the good and the bad that has happened, I’m incredibly grateful to each of the members of Suede for the music. Thanks a lot!</p>
        </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 23:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/suede1.html</guid>
    </item>

        <item>
        <title>Me and My Mind</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/my_mind.html</link>
        <description>
        <h1>Me and My Mind</h1>
        <h3>I wonder what was on my mind that day</h3>
        <h3>First published: 2nd March 2019</h3>
        <p>Believe it or not, when I was a teenager, I wanted to be a psychotherapist. I was told by a few people that I would be good at it but when I made it clear to some that I had some issues in the past, they warned me off it. I persisted for a little while but eventually got bored with the way in which the British school system teaches i.e. bombarding you with studies until you’re numb, rather than instilling an understanding of the overriding principles of psychological theories. I really wanted to get into psychotherapy to get to know more about the human condition and what makes people think and act the way they do and to help them out of some of the destructive ways that they live their lives. Starting to get the personal Jesus reference in the tagline? I also had an interest because I thought that if I had the tools to help others, I could help myself. This would be a trick that I would try to pull on myself again and again, but it doesn’t work.</p>
        <p>I think that it is a part of my personality to try and talk to people and get them to understand their own minds better. Proximity means that we cannot see the whole, so others have to act as mirrors. That doesn’t mean that we parrot back what we perceive as another person’s issue, it means listening as much as we can to the issues, context and history that we are given and making observations that may help to focus on other things that may cause these fractures. I have tried for a few months to put this into practice. Every now and then, I go to r/depression and talk to different people who have posted their experiences on there privately. Some people don’t respond, some get defensive but the majority are receptive, they really just want to be heard. That isn’t to say that I’m always a great help, most of the time I can only offer to listen. Sometimes, you can really get into a good conversation with some people and you actually feel like you have gotten somewhere.</p>
        <p>It’s amazing what causes us to have such extreme trauma, one person I chatted with stuck with me. She was from the US and was having issues with understandings around her heritage and the way that it affected the relationships of those around her. She hadn’t been up front with many people about where she was born, telling others that it was in Latin America rather than the US. I had mentioned that I had experienced changes because of the way I felt I had to change certain things about myself as a teenager. After talking about it, we pretty much agreed that her issue was difficult in the heat of the moment but that she could ask people to forgive her later. That was all pretty unique, but what I really took from it was something she wrote: “I think we’re almost kindred spirits in that sense, then. I definitely understand how the way you talk can be a sense of shame and insecurity.”</p>
        <p>The problem with all this is that you can only sustain this for so long before you start to lose your vitality and that is exactly what ended up happening to me. I couldn’t keep doing it for people. The conclusion that I have come to is that I cannot do this for others whilst simultaneously having no avenue for my own issues to really be discussed. I started to move back into a depressive state for a while but eventually managed to claw my way out. This wasn’t for long however, I then plunged into anhedonia. I no longer felt any real pleasure from anything that had once made me feel happy or content. Weirdly, the song “Suicide is Painless” began to sound like a taunt. When you can’t really feel anything, what can you do? The only thing that I found to help was meeting up and really talking with someone.</p>
        <p>And that is what is at the heart of the problem. The reason why suicide and depression are such common issues is because many people are either uncomfortable talking about their problems or don’t have anyone to talk about them with. The only way around it is to actually engage with people who are struggling. There are those who are lucky enough to have people around them who can help. Their friends and relatives can be a source of comfort and sometimes just a sympathetic ear to try to ease the burden of these anxieties. Often though, it isn’t obvious from conversations with people that you can necessarily tell that they need help. It’s often knowing the context and asking the right questions that can help you to figure this out. Other times, the problem is that people with isolate themselves away and that is something that needs to be overcome by similar means. It’s only by organising with each other that we can really help each other out. If we leave each other to our own devices, sometimes that can lead to people’s negativities taking over and then a self-imposed loneliness creeps in.</p>   
        </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 20:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/my_mind.html</guid>
    </item>

        <item>
        <title>Therapy?</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/therapy?.html</link>
        <description>
        <h1>Therapy?</h1>
        <h3>Well therapy before I actually first had proper therapy anyway</h3>
        <h3>First published: 2nd March 2019</h3>
        <p>[NOTE: This has some pretty unpleasant themes and I'm not sure everyone will be comfortable with what I have to say so I have hidden some stuff]</p>
        <p>Now there’s a question with a long and detailed (boring) answer. It would really help to break it up into little bite size sections and make it easy to digest even if it isn’t always easy to swallow. Since this is a pseudopsychological exploration that really just mimics a memoir of all the bits that made me this way, I’m going to do this is chronological order because that way, we can see how it built me up into being fucked. Since we’re trying to understand being fucked, I am going to focus mainly, but not exclusively on the negatives of life. Having said that, it might read as a sanitized version of what I would say in real life.</p>
        <h4>My Fucked-Up School Life</h4>
        <p>It all started when I was born. OK that’s not necessarily true. But really, I didn’t have the worst start. In fact, even though I was shy, unpopular and silly, my days in primary school were alright. I was teased a bit and there was a spot of bullying and threats here and there but I got through it well enough and by the time I got to grammar school, I actually kind of missed the place. I had a couple of good friends, one of which I’m actually still in contact with now (an epic achievement if you read on to find out what happened to most of the others), a girl who had a crush on me and I was smart, at least for the kids that were there.</p>
        <p>When I got to grammar school, something peculiar happened, I began to change my spots. This was inevitable, you might say, mimicking Freud poorly, and you would be right, but not necessarily for the reasons you think. I started to change my accent, not on purpose but since I was made a people pleaser, I had to fit in somehow. This is where my proficiency for learning and using accents came from. I have recently figured out that when I am hyperemotional, a trait I possess and even show from time to time as a sensitive soul, if I change my accent then I stop the outward show of emotion. Not every time, but most times it has worked like a charm. I have done accents for so long that I forgot why I even learned to do them. I’m miming someone else so I don’t have to be myself.</p>
        <p>If I had been myself, where would it have gotten me? Probably not very far, as that was the first thing I tried when making new friends. And make friends I did, all over in different groups, and I didn’t really spend a great deal of time with any of them so I didn’t really get that mixed up with them. This made for one lonely Sam, but he was too popular (I use that term loosely, think popular like syphilis rather than popular like Mandela) to notice. Of course, this did all come crumbling down when I was made to pick sides. I picked right most of the time as many of those who had been “friends” at one point soon showed their true colours. The friendship group I stuck with made me as popular as fart in an elevator with almost everyone else. I just wish I had waited to get closer to my floor before I shit my pants.</p>
        <p>With unpopularity comes its own issues. Of course, you won’t be getting any prizes with the in groups and you won’t be getting an easy time when your time comes. The problem is, that when you get into this situation, you don’t realise that it is a constant barrage. There are so many of them that there will always be one there to get you. On separate occasions, I was pinned down and drawn on which I had to obviously wash off before *I* got in trouble, poked in the eye in front of a teacher, had one sadist cut his hand up with a razor from a pencil sharpener and tell me that was what would happen to my face and my least favourite of all, I was punched in the kidney (I was always getting punched in the back) which meant I lied to my mum about having a urinary infection. What fun!</p>
        <p>When you get home from that, all you really want to do is play video games, ride a bike or maybe read a book. I did all those things, but of course, this is all too antisocial. So, I would text a friend to see what they were up to. Most of the time they would be busy with the huge amount of homework we all had to do (apparently a 12-year-old is supposed to do an hour and a half a night and it goes up every year) so I would try and watch TV. Being in a communal area has drawbacks however. Fighting with your brother and sister over what we’re watching, only having the TV until 6 because then the news would be on, then the soaps etc. but the major problem was dealing with my dad. At first, being the people pleaser that I am, I would agree to what he told me or begrudgingly acquiesce to his wish for me to get on with my homework. Fair enough.</p>
        <p>Later I would challenge the wisdom of the things that he was telling me. This was a mistake. It is normal for children to resent or be angry with their parents. But I was scared of my dad, and not in the “if he finds out what I’ve done, he’ll kill me” sort of way. I don’t know if he knew or understood but he always had a way of making me feel small. Constantly, I would have my way of doing things or understanding things but I could never be right. I felt stupid in a place where I was supposed to feel clever (grammar schools really do like to talk themselves up). So, I’d go to school, get bullied, feel small; come home, get belittled, feel small; repeat. That’s without mentioning the physical side of things. A little while ago, my dad, a man who had lifted me by the ears on multiple occasions (these were the butt of many taunts and I’m still sensitive about them today), told me that he used to use me as an example to my two younger siblings, because he knew that if I was going to be punished publicly then the other two wouldn’t do the same.</p>
        <p>As a result of this I was fearful of conflict for a very long time, I had witnessed and been a part of conflicts, as everyone else has, but I never felt like I would be heard or have my point of view respected. Not only that but I was immensely forgiving and have been ever since. Whilst I do like this about myself, it comes from the same place as the fear of conflict, I don’t feel like I matter so why continue the ill-feeling, I’ll end up losing out because of it anyway. I had a pretty warped understanding of masculinity from looking at the men around me but since that was what I knew, I thought that’s what I had to be. Deep down though, I wanted to have been born a girl at that point. I didn’t typify many of the male traits that I was supposed to and I found them to be totally contrived and pointless. Even now when I think about masculinity and being a man, it haunts me and makes me realise how I once acted and what kind of person I had been. I regret many of the things that I did at the time, in anger, rage, fury and with violence.</p>
        <p>Now I haven’t been open about this with many people because I’m not particularly happy with it being common knowledge but I need to write it down because it hurts to think that it has taken a hidden toll on me for the past few years. When I was 14, there was another guy in my PE class who used to hang around and make jokes with me and a friend of mine called Matt. During the summer, we would sometimes be sent to the cricket nets to do practice, which would mean that the teacher would go off for forty minutes to do actual sport with the athletic/popular guys. That’s when things began to be a problem. This guy used to make sexual jokes with us, like teenage boys do but then he’d proposition us. At first, he said it was a joke but later on, when it was just me and him, he pushed me up against the wire fencing and grabbed me in places I don’t really want to describe. I can’t really describe how I felt. When he knew he could get away with it, he’d do it again over the next few PE lessons and it progressive became more depraved. After a few weeks, I fought him off and he never bothered me again at school. I have since found out that he did the same to Matt, and I’ve felt a strange sense of guilt ever since.</p>
        <h4>Sixth-Form</h4>
        <p>Moving from year-11 to sixth-form felt great. We had left behind the heteronormative masculine bullshit of an all-boys setting and returned to a mixed-sex group that was free of much of the cliquey nonsense that had preceded it. That’s not to say that cliques were not around, just their significance had diminished. It wasn’t weird to talk to people outside of your normal friendship group, it was normal to get along with people who had completely different interests and popularity wasn’t governed by rules around what the latest trends were. A lot of these people were actually pretty cool.</p>
        <p>With the choice of a variety of different subjects, I decided to take a smorgasbord approach. What this did for me academically is not too clear, but what it did for me socially was expand my horizons. I met more and more people during this period and even though I was not particularly sociable, which is not a great surprise given the circumstances, I managed to have a wide and interesting group of friends and acquaintances. They mainly consisted of two distinct groups. One the one hand was a group of people who I had known of from 11, but had only just come into contact with on a regular basis because of a circumstance that I’ll discuss soon. They were mainly very artsy, and usually pretty conceited but actually they were lovely people. We used to talk a lot about different things that we were interested in and they would invariably have different interests to me. Then there was the group of friends I made in my history and politics classes who were all pretty similar to me but were usually younger. Musically in particular, they put me onto things that I would have come too maybe a decade or more later they were so ahead of the curve.</p>
        <p>The first group of friends I came to hang out with by chance. One of the friends in particular, I met up with purely by coincidence. This coincidence led me to hanging out a couple of times with them in Rochester and so I met their extended network. That’s when I met my first girlfriend. She was interesting and we had a fair few things in common. For the first six months, we were having a blast but then three issues came into play. The first was me. I was trying to act out a masculine persona that was never me but it was the mask that I felt I had to wear because I was a “man” whilst simultaneously trying to deal with the toxicity of my past. The second was that my then girlfriend was difficult to please and took to using numerous emotional tools as a weapon to punish or scold. For a long time, I thought that this was normal, but it took me a long time to find out that I was very wrong. Thirdly, a very dark figure reappeared in my life. Unbeknownst to me until it was too late, I stayed at the house of the very person who had assaulted me when I was 14. I had a total breakdown. For something that had such an effect on me, I had just put it out of my mind, as I have tried to every other day of my life, largely successfully.</p>
        <p>So, when things fell apart, there should have been a feeling of inevitability about it right? Oddly enough, if I had stuck to my guns it may never have happened. Or more likely it would have been worse and I wouldn’t be writing this. My girlfriend asked me if I wanted to go to a friend’s party, but I really wasn’t interested, I just didn’t feel up to it. She insisted and I caved. When we got there, I started having a good time but there was an edge and a bitterness that I couldn’t understand to me. I felt isolated and angry and with the conceited, bullshit entitlement that only heteronormative masculinity [I paid for my degree, and I’m going to use it, damn it] can provide. I started an argument with her. Then when it didn’t go my way, I pushed and pulled her. Then I messaged for her parents to pick her up, probably the best thing I could have done. I remember walking home and realising that I had fucked up. Really fucked up.</p>
        <h4>Leaving Home</h4>
        <p>So, I went to stay with my grandparents after the inevitable end of the relationship. First it was to get me away from Chatham, but later it was so I could just have the time and space to focus on things. I had finally broken down completely and I had to rebuild myself. The main problem was figuring out if I even wanted to. After what I had done, how the fuck could I forgive myself? That became a recurring thought over the next couple of years. I was finally beginning to understand that all of the things that has been going on in my life up until that point has had an impact on putting me in the position that I was in. I reached out to friends but they were not interested by and large, and who could blame them. This was the beginning of a larger problem that would plague me later in life.</p>
        <p>So, the process began with trying to free myself from the shackles of anger. When I spoke to the Samaritans, they would ask me where I thought my anger came from? I would always answer, “my dad”. He’s an angry and, in some ways, paranoid man and has no issue with dressing people down in public; he’s the perfect candidate. Of course, it was far larger than that but he was and is <em>the</em> key figure. The fact was that my anger was really just a way of my depressive tendencies to unleash themselves upon the world. The other major way was lying, whether it be my impulsive, compulsive need to tell lies at times, to the accents and acting that I performed for people. It was a horrible period to go through but after a year of having no school, no job and no life [apart from visiting Simon in London, I’ll never be able to thank you enough] it was time to move on.</p>
        <p>In September 2010, I moved to London to study history at UEL. The first week was a bit much but after I settled in, I found a good bunch of people on and around campus to hang around with. It was great to be sociable and talk about anything without actually worrying (too much) about my past. Having gotten through it all, I didn’t have to share it with anyone else. At first, it was a disparate bunch who really just loved doing what everyone loves doing at that age, getting drunk, going to parties and having fun. It was good fun, but me being me, I had to go and get involved in something else. I started going to talks and lectures with a socialist student society and met with a few of the group socially later. Towards the end of the semester, the cuts to education and the tripling of tuition fees led us to protest and to occupy part of a main building on the campus. We obviously weren’t successful, but many of the friendships I made there have changed my outlook on life totally.</p>
        <p>We all ended up moving in together in a huge house in Leytonstone. Having such a radically different life to the one I had been leading, I started to feel a confidence that I never really had previously. These people were great fun to be around and I tried my best to impress them and to keep them entertained at times. The truth is that I looked up to most of them as they appeared to be so at ease with the world whereas I was constantly worried about the metaphysical substance of the world, or whether or not I had much of a place in it or mostly, experiencing the moment for what it is. About half way through my second year, I was with someone who they didn’t really get along with and so I ended up trying to work with both sides to make them happy. Thinking back now, I shouldn’t have carried on with the non-relationship I was in as it clearly wasn’t going anywhere, I remember remarking on it at the time, but also because she bit my penis. Yes, you read that correctly, she put her teeth into my penis and bit down. It is any wonder I’m fucked up?</p>
        <p>It was never going to be enough though. The summer of my second year, I really felt awful about everything. Depression had returned and really sunk its teeth into me. I was barely sleeping, not really interacting with people as much as I had done and I felt like my world was coming to an end. This should have prompted me to seek help, but instead I decided to try and get through it in my own way. It worked for the time being and when I moved in to a new house with my friends that December, I was happy and set for a new place to discover and I had gotten closer to another group of people through these friends who were amazing people, who really were great fun to be around. One friend had always been fun to be around, but things had started to change for him, as they had for me. He was beginning to have a crisis at the same time that I was and it made for a terrible situation.</p>
        <p>Firstly, I lost my dissertation just weeks before the hand in date. I panicked. I tried so many different ways to get it back that I had run out of animals to sacrifice and was having to move on to people. At one stage, after realising it had all gone wrong, I just laid down and thought, “there is nothing left”. Depression was back, and it wanted to take me as low as I could go. I went to the doctors and they prescribed me citalopram. This was a mistake, if my GP had looked, he would know that there are serious side effects to taking it if under 24 and they proved to be huge. At the same time, another friend was having a schizophrenic episode and was ideating in an odd way. He came around the house one day and after a short discussion, I thought I would go for my daily walk as I always would with citalopram.</p>
        <p>He asked if he could come along too and I obliged. When we got to a point along a main road, he stopped. I stopped and turned and he said that this was his house. He invited me in and proceeded to sit and look at me in silence for a few minutes. He then told me, “I keep thinking I should kill myself”, part way through a conversation about the horrible things that he had been told to do. I was worried, but in a zombie state. I went back to the house and tried to slowly and calmly explain what had happened and we all returned to his house. Upon returning to him, he accidently took an overdose of sleeping pills and they had to take him to hospital. A few days later, I tried to do the same. I tried but the impulse to live kicked in at a critical point. It is the only time that I have ever felt like that in my life, like I had reached the bottom and bounced so hard that I was almost in a normal space for an hour. It wasn’t euphoric, it just felt like a switch had been turned back on.</p>
        <p>But that wasn’t the end of this particular saga. One of my very best friends in the world was having a torrid time and her boyfriend, as I mentioned a few paragraphs ago, was really starting to feel the strain. At one point, I was down again and walked around Hampstead Heath trying to find something to make me feel better. After failing miserably, I decided to return home. Upon getting back, I sat down and started to contemplate a few things. Soon after, my friend’s boyfriend came through the door. To put a long story short, he wanted me to conspire with him to kill another friend of mine. I was dumbfounded. Another friend of ours came in and asked why we weren’t watching the football. That break in things allowed me to think and when he left, I did shortly after. I walked up to the house of my threatened friend and all seemed fine, so I called my mum and explained what was going on and that I would be returning home tomorrow.</p>
        <p>The next day, I got up and went downstairs and all my roommates, apart from him were there, stone-faced. I only needed to enquire if it was about him before we all looked at each other and saw what was going on. I explained what had happened to me, and they were gobsmacked. We all went to check on our friend and I explained what had happened. What I saw hurt me deeply, he was distraught. It was then decided that I and another housemate would confront him. I stood facing him and explained that everyone knew. I have never seen someone physically shrink before my eyes before but he almost cowered. I still wasn’t stupid enough to think that we were safe though, so we carried on talking until his partner came and took him to hospital. I know that this hurt all of my friends there at the time, but it really tested me and my ability to function. I was broken again.</p>
        <h4>Recovery (Attempt One)</h4>
        <p>I returned home, tail between my legs, broken, dishevelled and lacking the one thing that I relied upon to keep me going when I was in London (and anywhere else for that matter), companionship. The friendships that I had made in London gave me a tremendous sense of support but after the events that took place, I knew that I could neither stay there, nor talk to them for a while as we all tried to come to terms with the trauma of it all. In fact, this was the last time I actually had any friendships this tight and this strong and I miss them immensely at times. This isn’t to say that many of the friendships that I have now aren’t meaningful, it’s just that the experiences we shared certainly drew us together and that experience helped push us apart. As such, I have to say that with no guilt or shame, I do bear a strong amount of ill-will to the person who managed to put us all in the situation we were in. I understand that many will sympathise with him, and I have no qualms with that, but what happened throughout those years, unbeknownst to me, shook my ability to trust.</p>
        <p>I had to retake part of my course in my fourth year of university because they wouldn’t give me an extension on any of my final modules. As you can probably tell, I have strong resentment towards the university for that still. In having to commute from home so much, I realised that I needed a job to keep me going. I got a job that Christmas working as an elf in Santa’s Grotto at a local garden centre. Yes, I was living the dream ladies and gentlemen. Whilst there I met a guy, and we went out drinking a few times. After our time at the garden centre, I met up with him a couple more times and on one occasion, he invited someone he was interested in out too. She brought her friends along with her who didn’t look overly impressed! One of them I liked immediately. We all had a few drinks and then the woman’s friends left and we drank as a trio. After a series of conversations, the girl I liked was witty, interesting and always had a great point to make. After I found out that my “friend” intended to cheat on his girlfriend with her friend, things ended up being even more interesting. Eventually we all ended up out together one night and we got quite tipsy. That was the beginning of our relationship.</p>
        <p>After a little while together we became inseparable. We went away together a few times and tried to spend as much time with each other as possible. The natural progression therefore was that we move in together. Just a few catches to that. Firstly, renting in Maidstone was so prohibitively expensive that it really wouldn’t have been worth our while doing so. Secondly, I didn’t have a job and was trying to save up with whatever cash I could scratch together. Finally, we were so absolutely done with having to be around our parents and families that we decided we couldn’t just stick around for a while. We decided on Liverpool, a fun, metropolitan city with a great culture. Great to visit, many things to see and do and easy on the eye too.</p>
        <p>It took me a while to find my feet but after a four-week unpaid work placement, I was given a job in accounts at a fast-growing hotel chain. It took some time to get into the swing of how it all worked and what I was really doing but when I got into it, it was a pretty decent job. The problem was that me and my other half just didn’t really fit in. We liked the place at first but began to really dislike it towards the end of our first year there. Our relationship was going strong but there was strain being placed on it by being stress by what was going on around us. I was irritable and she was nearing depression. It was getting to be too much and we needed to get out. Luckily, we had both come into some money after our families had saved for us. We were coming up for a healthy deposit for a house and although we looked at a few different places in Liverpool, we ended up saying to each other that we needed to leave, and so we returned to Maidstone a little over a year after we had left.</p>
        <p>Returning to live with your parents is never easy nor fun, but when you have spent so much time with someone who meant so much to you, everyday for the past year, it was pretty torturous, not to mention the fact that we had two dogs that we adopted in Liverpool with us too. After a brief debate, we settled on buying in Maidstone. After a while, we got lucky, found a place, bought it and moved in. It felt like the start of something huge. I was not wrong. A couple of months after we had moved in, I began having mental health issues again, but I couldn’t really find solace or help anywhere. In the end, I was told by my other half to sort myself out because she was worried about me. In a panic, I did entirely the wrong thing and buried it away. After changing jobs and earning more I started to feel better for a while but it had come back as an irritability again that I just couldn’t shift. After the previous time, I was having issues being open and honest. It was at this point that my other half was having health problems of her own. They started out as one thing but then became multiple issues. In the time that she was ill, she spent sometime alone. With this time, she made a decision; after 4 and a half years, it was time to go our separate ways. I can’t say I understand why still but I accepted that I couldn’t change the way she felt. I was back in 2013 again. Broken, alone and in need of answers.</p>
        <p>That’s why I am writing this. I don’t know where to start and I have no idea where this will finish but I need to find out why I am still having these doubts about myself and why I cannot seem to find my place in the world.</p>    
        </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 17:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/therapy?.html</guid>
    </item>

        <item>
        <title>Critiquing Ideology. Challenging Rules.</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/cicr.html</link>
        <description>
        <h1>Critiquing Ideology. Challenging Rules.</h1>
        <h3>My first proper post. Don't say I didn't warn you.</h3>
        <h3>First published: 1st March 2019</h3>
        <p>When I first read Gramsci’s work, I didn’t really get it. The translation that I read was old and written with an academic tone that almost said “you have to be one of us to understand”. I proceeded to try again and again until it began to fall into place. With many emancipatory understandings, you expect a euphoria, or the feeling that some shackles have been loosened, or most commonly that it would be like a blindfold had finally been ripped away and you were finally able to see the light. The truth was more terrifying. If anyone has seen the film, <em>They Live </em>by John Carpenter starring Rowdy Roddy Piper, they’ll understand what I mean when I say it’s the opposite. This film is one of the most obvious displays of how ideology works. John Nada finds a pair of sunglasses and when he puts them on, he sees things for what they really are.</p>
        <p>Hegemonic ideology is the foundation of our understanding of life and what we see around us and affects our every action and reaction. An example is when someone does work for a family member and even though may have been simple, easy and may not have actually cost anything, there is an insistence from the family member who needed help to offer money as recompense. In this situation, the person who helped will insist as fervently that they will not take any money as it was simple and they were doing it as a kindness. The two family members are essentially playing a game to see how nice they are. Another example is when someone offers the last of something, the implication is that everyone else refuse so that they can enjoy it, although not everyone falls for this ploy of being nice.</p>
        <p>These are quite small examples and they show us exactly how it permeates throughout our daily lives, but it works on a huge level as <em>They Live </em>shows us. This cultural supremacy, is not the result of coercion. This is a fundamental problem for those who view hegemony in terms of a struggle, particularly those who view it from a class struggle standpoint. The continuance of ideology is based on consent. This is not the same as saying that people want to view the world this way or that they even understand what is going on but it requires that people do not challenge it and accept its rules and the regulation of daily life implicitly. This is not to say that every ideology is the same, or even that it is constant. It is very much an open-ended phenomenon, else it would not have been able to develop from what had gone before and would not be able to develop into something else.</p>
        <p>Ideology in this sense is a cultural hegemony and can therefore can affect different nations, socioeconomic groups and even family relations. One of my lecturers once said that he went to his wife’s parents for Christmas and they brought out the tin of chocolates to share. He took a handful and immediately saw the looks on the faces of his parents-in-law. This was a faux pas whereas in his own family this would have been completely normal. Of course, this is comparing apples and pears when looking at this example and perhaps white supremacy but it follows that there are unwritten rules that we do not challenge. But, and admittedly this is only my inference, there is an acceptance here that whilst you were offered an abundance, you should submit to frugality. This of course is not the same as the ideology of the KKK, who although they told themselves and each other that they were the purest Christian fundamentalists and therefore good, giving and charitable, whilst killing black men and raping black women. Wait a fucking minute, how does that work?</p>
        <p>Cultural hegemony is not just how you follow the rules, it is also about how you break them. If I was going out drinking as a teenager or a young adult, my parents would have been ok with this and would have accepted this as a part of growing up. However, if I were to ever do this in front of them then I would be punished. But it goes the other way too, those who follow the rules too well can also be punished. Slavoj Žižek uses the example of Stalin giving a speech and then opening a public debate of what he had said. The first person stands up and criticises Stalin and what he had to say. We all know that his friends would be asking who saw him last the morning after. A second person interjects and confronts him stating that no one can talk about comrade Stalin in that manner. He would have been even luckier to wake up in the morning.</p>
        <p>So, what do we do about this? The problem is to avoid cynicism and find a way of piecing together an understanding of the world whilst repelling the unseen hand of ideology. Like the fight scene in <em>They Live</em>, you can’t always make others understand the way that you do. It is important though to look around and get accustomed to seeking out these unwritten rules that govern things and challenge their supremacy and often their idiocy. It needs to be looked at, understood and challenged over and over again before it really starts to make sense. How does it affect you? Discovering how it really comes into your life is the best way of coming to terms with it.</p>  
        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 17:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/cicr.html</guid>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>
