<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>Wamsicks</title>
    <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.wamsicks.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>Wamsicks Blog Posts</description>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 10:06:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <ttl>1721901998</ttl>
    
    <item>
        <title>A Punch</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/a_punch.html</link>
        <description><
        <h1>A Punch</h1>
        <h3>Returning to the scene of the crime</h3>
	    <h3>First published: 15th June 2020</h3>
        <p>I want to talk about that thing. Yeah, THAT THING. I’m sure you are aware (if you know me that is) that last year at around this time, I was assaulted. Long story short, I was walking to catch a bus after getting off the train, a guy came after me swearing and telling me that I nudged him (not that I had noticed). He proceeded to push me, then try to trip me, then punched me from behind (because he was a coward, obviously). My jaw was broken, on the right side of my face (my left) the mandible was totally broken into two pieces, at my chin the mandible was fractured. After a pretty terrible time of dealing with A&amp;E under the Tories, which consisted of waiting four hours before being seen whilst I was spitting or swallowing massive amounts of my own blood, stayed with my parents and they took me to a hospital about an hour and a half away for me to have surgery. It was a great success; I have to say. One colleague even remarked that I looked as handsome as ever! Three major issues have crept up in my mind arising from this event: my interaction with the police, my mental health and my view and perception of other people.</p>
        <p>I wasn’t the one to go to the police, my parents were, and the police were slow to get around to actually interviewing me. In fact, it was almost two weeks until they finally got around to it. When they finally did, I was asked the question “what do you hope to get from this”? At that moment, I knew where I stood. I told him that I wanted the person to be identified so that it could be stopped from happening again. Inside, all my instincts were being justified: I thought it would be a waste of time to involve the police as nothing good would come of it. In fact, I would have to ring up to get CCTV footage from the bus company just so there was some footage of the person who did it. I never heard back about it and I never expect to.</p>
        <p>This didn’t help me to feel particularly good mentally. The aftermath of what had happened was actually an uptick in my emotions towards everything. I didn’t feel fear or an anger, I just wanted to get on with it and get back to things. During my time waiting for surgery and even immediately after coming around, I was chatting and joking with the nurses who were taking care of me. Maybe the fact that they had taken such good care of me and where willing to make me feel better helped with that. It wasn’t until a few weeks had passed and I was getting back to my normal routine that I realised that I wasn’t right mentally. There were a few times when I went to town with my then girlfriend and thought that I was being followed or that someone was trying to come for me or intimidate me. I was dealing with anxiety for the first time since school. I struggled to go out and do things as I normally would and my frustrations boiling over probably led to us breaking up. It was the breakup the finally pushed me to get help.</p>
        <p>Through the company’s EAP scheme, I was able to see a therapist and finally work through some of the things that had happened and deal with the stress and rage that had come about from it. She was fantastic and a great help. I opened up about my torrid past and even though I had been passed though because of what happened to me that year, we ended up dealing with a large range of things that I covered in a previous post. Looking at this as a continuum rather than separate events made me realise that I was dealing well with the situation I was dealt. When you are used to crisis, terrible things shock you less. I even told her that this wouldn’t make my top three worst things that have happened to me and she saw that although I was struggling, that coping strategies would help me to keep on going without having the breakdown that I may have been due.</p>
        <p>The problem is that I was still struggling to relate to a world that felt fundamentally different to the one that I had conceived of. Was it a contrived gaze or was the situation shaking my expectations of the way things are? I suppose both were true. I have always been idealistic, and this continues to be the case but now I have a more nuanced view of people that I did. When you believe that the world needs to be changed to be fundamentally fairer so that we can all benefit from a just society, the immediate impact of a fist breaking your jaw isn’t “well here’s some proof!” For a long time, I questioned whether people could be trusted at all. Luckily this didn’t last too long as I was able to see the contradictions in this logic of nihilism. The more pernicious problem was my relationships to people closer to me.</p>
        <p>Before surgery, I posted on Facebook about what had happened and about some of the great support I had received from many of my friends and colleagues. I received a flood of positive messages and many people messaged to see how I was getting on. After that initial flurry, came the people who would stick by me and lend a hand when I needed it. Except, that didn’t happen. A couple of friends came to see me and checked up on me but the vast majority who posted nice massages haven’t actually messaged me since. It’s almost like I had been forgotten. I don’t want to sound like I’m attacking anyone but after a few months without anyone checking in, I felt the way I did the last time something terrible happened, like I had been abandoned. I don’t know what else I was supposed to expect really, I haven’t built close relationships with anyone new for a long time, partly because the circumstances have meant that I don’t keep in touch or because I struggle mentally with interacting when I don’t see people very often. Perhaps I have idealised my (apparently) longer lasting friendships too much. Perhaps the sands of time laid waste to these relationships and I hadn’t seen it.</p>
        <p>What would have been nice though, is to have had an inkling that this might have been the case. It’s bewildering to realise that the people you have valorised no longer hold you in the same level of esteem. It’s dumbfounding to realise that you haven’t moved on when they have. It’s traumatic to think that perhaps it had always been this way.</p>
        <p>I meant to write this last year, but the last paragraph was too difficult to articulate until now. Especially in the context of knowing I have very limited outlets for expression and reciprocation, I have a couple of people who I can talk to and I am very grateful for that. I hope this doesn’t sound like hyperbole. I don’t want to cause friction and neither do I want to hurt anyone else, but the truth is that because I don’t value myself, I don’t have plans, I don’t have dreams and I don’t look to the future.</p>  
        > </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 12:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/a_punch.html</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>What's it all about?</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/wiaa.html</link>
        <description><
        <h1>What’s it all about?</h1>
        <h3>I don't know, don't ask me</h3>
	    <h3>First published: 6th January 2020</h3>
        <p>Ontologically, I mean. For those who daren’t ask, that’s when you think about what it means to be. Usually, I like to divide myself from fantasy or at least put myself into fantasy that is so foreign or barren that it is too distinct from my reality to me confuse it. Unfortunately (or fortunately depending on your outlook), when something gets to you and really takes you along for the ride, the fantasy is inescapable.</p>
        <p>When you are presented with a depiction of an alternative reality, even if it is ghastly and morbid, it can sometimes force you to confront your reality and make you ask uncomfortable questions about it. Here I am, living a comfortable life, doing well enough, but the feeling constant nagging away at me is that there has to be something bigger and better out there to do, to be a part of. Good fantasy can fill you with excitement and dread and that is precisely what it did and it made me question whether or not I had experienced similar feelings recently. In all honesty, I cannot remember the last time I felt that kind of thrill. I am not writing this to say that live ought to be exciting and full of boundless fun, but I am saying that it need not be so mundane.</p>
        <p>I get the feeling that I am not the only person that feels this way and that this life is not the one that they wanted to have. I hear from some that this is the reality of what you deal with later in life. I hear from others that I should be more grateful for what I have. To have gratitude for salvation from scarcity is one thing, but I cannot bring myself to accept banality. Perhaps I am at fault for this as my choice to spurn the magic of inspiration on too many occasions could mean that I may well have run dry or, it may be that working has taken away vital time and energy from the divine impulse of creativity. Either way, it is remarkable that a couple of hours of someone else’s wonderous light has set the fire of my mind burning.</p>
        <p>I hope that this will return me to a better and fuller time, but I have my doubts. In the meantime, I will seize upon the opportunities that creativity gives to me when it sees fit.</p>
        > </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/wiaa.html</guid>
    </item>

        <item>
        <title>Tears of Suburbia</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/suede1.html</link>
        <description><
        <h1>Tears of Suburbia</h1>
        <h3>A love letter to Suede</h3>
        <h3>First published: 27th April 2019</h3>
        <p>When I look back at some of the pivotal moments of my life, it seems weird to me that one of the most significant events that happened to me was going to YouTube and playing a song, but that is one of the idiosyncratic things about life, little moments can have profound consequences. I was very into heavy metal, grunge and punk before I turned 16 and after then I had started to listen to a much wider variety of music. At 17 and 18, I was particularly fond of British indie in the 80s and 90s; Britpop and shoegazing were mainstays on the playlist of the Creative Zen mp3 player I had at the time. Blur especially were a huge draw for me, I like the way that Damon Albarn looked, sang, the stuff he’d talked about and I particularly like what he said to Tony Blair when he was invited to hobnob with New Labour and their sycophants. I read up on him a little bit and learned about his relationship with Justine Frischmann. For some bizarre reason, when I heard that she was with another guy in a band called Suede before, I was a bit apprehensive about them and when I saw Brett Anderson’s face for the first time, I intensely disliked them.</p>
        <p>After breaking up with my then girlfriend, I was in a bad place and doing a fair bit of soul-searching. I was challenging a lot of the feelings that I had about life and myself in general, but I knew that I wasn’t going to find any real comfort in what surrounded me. Most of the people I had as friends had either gone to university or had deserted me for a variety of reasons and my family was less help because although they are great for practical and structural support, emotionally or psychologically I would not know where to start with them. I wanted to expand my horizons with music still and I kept seeing that Suede had been an influence on many of the bands that I liked at the time so I decided that this was the time to finally just bite the bullet and give them a listen.</p>
        <p>That first listen was surreal. I listened to the same song about 15 times in a row before moving on to the next one and the next one. Animal Nitrate to this day is the song that if hear it in passing, I have to stop and listen, if not sing along to. I went walking from my parent’s house in Chatham down to the charity shops in Rochester to look at the old CDs and LPs as I didn’t have much cash at the time. I ended up finding a Suede single, with a pig in a bright blue suit and a red tie on and bought it for 50p. I opened the case and found it was the Animal Nitrate single. As soon as I got home, I played it on repeat. Painted People became another one of my favourites and I loved the versatility they showed as a band to make something as great as The Big Time.</p>
        <p>In the next few months I bought their first four albums, I would have bought their fifth and final album (at the time) but I couldn’t seem to get it anywhere. I listened to their eponymous first, repeatedly and was in awe of what I was hearing, the drums and bass created a backdrop for Bernard Butler to unleash arpeggio after arpeggio into each track, he played with purpose, completely different to anyone else I’ve heard before or since. But it was the voice, and more importantly the words, of Brett Anderson that stuck me. His high pitched, half falsetto is not easy to imitate and immediately strikes you as beyond what most singers would sound like. The words shared a similarly abstract quality.</p>
        <p>The effect that Brett’s androgyny had on me was massive, the words often carried a sexual quality and whether or not the songs were about fucking or not, their always had a debase sensibility, as Bernard mentions about The Living Dead, “I've written this really beautiful piece of music and it's a squalid song about junkies.” It made me focus too on the false way in which so many things were put into black and white choices in life and that there is a way in which society designs the way that we have to interact with everything about each other and ourselves. In the most extreme case, it made me think a lot about gender. I wasn’t comfortable with the way that I perceived myself at the time, I was trying to play up to a masculine stereotype that has never really felt like me. That’s not to say I don’t have masculine traits, it’s just that there are many masculine traits that I haven’t internalised very well or that I actively despise. Equally, I feel I do have so feminine traits, which some people are only to happy to remind me of. Listening to these lyrics allowed me to be more comfortable about this and gave me the push to actually take these questions on directly.</p>
        <p>Moving away to London was a big change for me, it was the first time that I had really been away from family for an extended period. Strangely, I had listened to Suede, Coming Up and Head Music but not Dog Man Star at this point. Why? I honestly am still not sure but there was something in my brain that said don’t listen to it yet. I’m glad I waited. From September through to December 2010, I didn’t listen to much else and it was an almost religious experience. I am still a bit obsessed with the album now. It appeared heavily on the setlist when I saw them for the first time at the O2 that December. I just remember getting back that evening and thinking, I need to see them again. Sure enough, I bought tickets for the three gigs they were doing at the Brixton Academy in the coming May, one album a night for each of their first three albums. When it came around to it, I was buzzing. Standing in line, I couldn’t wait for it to start. A guy behind me in the line asked for a photo and we got talking about all sorts of stuff, music, sports, politics etc. Over the coming nights, I ended up chatting to him more and more. Eight years on, Dave and I are really good mates and he’s one of the few people that I can rely on.</p>
        <p>They have given me more than I really thought musicians ever could, and I haven’t even met them! So, for all the good and the bad that has happened, I’m incredibly grateful to each of the members of Suede for the music. Thanks a lot!</p>
        > </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 23:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/suede1.html</guid>
    </item>

        <item>
        <title>Me and My Mind</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/my_mind.html</link>
        <description><
        <h1>Me and My Mind</h1>
        <h3>I wonder what was on my mind that day</h3>
        <h3>First published: 2nd March 2019</h3>
        <p>Believe it or not, when I was a teenager, I wanted to be a psychotherapist. I was told by a few people that I would be good at it but when I made it clear to some that I had some issues in the past, they warned me off it. I persisted for a little while but eventually got bored with the way in which the British school system teaches i.e. bombarding you with studies until you’re numb, rather than instilling an understanding of the overriding principles of psychological theories. I really wanted to get into psychotherapy to get to know more about the human condition and what makes people think and act the way they do and to help them out of some of the destructive ways that they live their lives. Starting to get the personal Jesus reference in the tagline? I also had an interest because I thought that if I had the tools to help others, I could help myself. This would be a trick that I would try to pull on myself again and again, but it doesn’t work.</p>
        <p>I think that it is a part of my personality to try and talk to people and get them to understand their own minds better. Proximity means that we cannot see the whole, so others have to act as mirrors. That doesn’t mean that we parrot back what we perceive as another person’s issue, it means listening as much as we can to the issues, context and history that we are given and making observations that may help to focus on other things that may cause these fractures. I have tried for a few months to put this into practice. Every now and then, I go to r/depression and talk to different people who have posted their experiences on there privately. Some people don’t respond, some get defensive but the majority are receptive, they really just want to be heard. That isn’t to say that I’m always a great help, most of the time I can only offer to listen. Sometimes, you can really get into a good conversation with some people and you actually feel like you have gotten somewhere.</p>
        <p>It’s amazing what causes us to have such extreme trauma, one person I chatted with stuck with me. She was from the US and was having issues with understandings around her heritage and the way that it affected the relationships of those around her. She hadn’t been up front with many people about where she was born, telling others that it was in Latin America rather than the US. I had mentioned that I had experienced changes because of the way I felt I had to change certain things about myself as a teenager. After talking about it, we pretty much agreed that her issue was difficult in the heat of the moment but that she could ask people to forgive her later. That was all pretty unique, but what I really took from it was something she wrote: “I think we’re almost kindred spirits in that sense, then. I definitely understand how the way you talk can be a sense of shame and insecurity.”</p>
        <p>The problem with all this is that you can only sustain this for so long before you start to lose your vitality and that is exactly what ended up happening to me. I couldn’t keep doing it for people. The conclusion that I have come to is that I cannot do this for others whilst simultaneously having no avenue for my own issues to really be discussed. I started to move back into a depressive state for a while but eventually managed to claw my way out. This wasn’t for long however, I then plunged into anhedonia. I no longer felt any real pleasure from anything that had once made me feel happy or content. Weirdly, the song “Suicide is Painless” began to sound like a taunt. When you can’t really feel anything, what can you do? The only thing that I found to help was meeting up and really talking with someone.</p>
        <p>And that is what is at the heart of the problem. The reason why suicide and depression are such common issues is because many people are either uncomfortable talking about their problems or don’t have anyone to talk about them with. The only way around it is to actually engage with people who are struggling. There are those who are lucky enough to have people around them who can help. Their friends and relatives can be a source of comfort and sometimes just a sympathetic ear to try to ease the burden of these anxieties. Often though, it isn’t obvious from conversations with people that you can necessarily tell that they need help. It’s often knowing the context and asking the right questions that can help you to figure this out. Other times, the problem is that people with isolate themselves away and that is something that needs to be overcome by similar means. It’s only by organising with each other that we can really help each other out. If we leave each other to our own devices, sometimes that can lead to people’s negativities taking over and then a self-imposed loneliness creeps in.</p>   
        > </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 20:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/my_mind.html</guid>
    </item>

        <item>
        <title>Therapy?</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/therapy?.html</link>
        <description><
        <h1>A Punch</h1>
        <h3>Returning to the scene of the crime</h3>
	    <h3>First published: 15th June 2020</h3>
        <p>I want to talk about that thing. Yeah, THAT THING. I’m sure you are aware (if you know me that is) that last year at around this time, I was assaulted. Long story short, I was walking to catch a bus after getting off the train, a guy came after me swearing and telling me that I nudged him (not that I had noticed). He proceeded to push me, then try to trip me, then punched me from behind (because he was a coward, obviously). My jaw was broken, on the right side of my face (my left) the mandible was totally broken into two pieces, at my chin the mandible was fractured. After a pretty terrible time of dealing with A&amp;E under the Tories, which consisted of waiting four hours before being seen whilst I was spitting or swallowing massive amounts of my own blood, stayed with my parents and they took me to a hospital about an hour and a half away for me to have surgery. It was a great success; I have to say. One colleague even remarked that I looked as handsome as ever! Three major issues have crept up in my mind arising from this event: my interaction with the police, my mental health and my view and perception of other people.</p>
        <p>I wasn’t the one to go to the police, my parents were, and the police were slow to get around to actually interviewing me. In fact, it was almost two weeks until they finally got around to it. When they finally did, I was asked the question “what do you hope to get from this”? At that moment, I knew where I stood. I told him that I wanted the person to be identified so that it could be stopped from happening again. Inside, all my instincts were being justified: I thought it would be a waste of time to involve the police as nothing good would come of it. In fact, I would have to ring up to get CCTV footage from the bus company just so there was some footage of the person who did it. I never heard back about it and I never expect to.</p>
        <p>This didn’t help me to feel particularly good mentally. The aftermath of what had happened was actually an uptick in my emotions towards everything. I didn’t feel fear or an anger, I just wanted to get on with it and get back to things. During my time waiting for surgery and even immediately after coming around, I was chatting and joking with the nurses who were taking care of me. Maybe the fact that they had taken such good care of me and where willing to make me feel better helped with that. It wasn’t until a few weeks had passed and I was getting back to my normal routine that I realised that I wasn’t right mentally. There were a few times when I went to town with my then girlfriend and thought that I was being followed or that someone was trying to come for me or intimidate me. I was dealing with anxiety for the first time since school. I struggled to go out and do things as I normally would and my frustrations boiling over probably led to us breaking up. It was the breakup the finally pushed me to get help.</p>
        <p>Through the company’s EAP scheme, I was able to see a therapist and finally work through some of the things that had happened and deal with the stress and rage that had come about from it. She was fantastic and a great help. I opened up about my torrid past and even though I had been passed though because of what happened to me that year, we ended up dealing with a large range of things that I covered in a previous post. Looking at this as a continuum rather than separate events made me realise that I was dealing well with the situation I was dealt. When you are used to crisis, terrible things shock you less. I even told her that this wouldn’t make my top three worst things that have happened to me and she saw that although I was struggling, that coping strategies would help me to keep on going without having the breakdown that I may have been due.</p>
        <p>The problem is that I was still struggling to relate to a world that felt fundamentally different to the one that I had conceived of. Was it a contrived gaze or was the situation shaking my expectations of the way things are? I suppose both were true. I have always been idealistic, and this continues to be the case but now I have a more nuanced view of people that I did. When you believe that the world needs to be changed to be fundamentally fairer so that we can all benefit from a just society, the immediate impact of a fist breaking your jaw isn’t “well here’s some proof!” For a long time, I questioned whether people could be trusted at all. Luckily this didn’t last too long as I was able to see the contradictions in this logic of nihilism. The more pernicious problem was my relationships to people closer to me.</p>
        <p>Before surgery, I posted on Facebook about what had happened and about some of the great support I had received from many of my friends and colleagues. I received a flood of positive messages and many people messaged to see how I was getting on. After that initial flurry, came the people who would stick by me and lend a hand when I needed it. Except, that didn’t happen. A couple of friends came to see me and checked up on me but the vast majority who posted nice massages haven’t actually messaged me since. It’s almost like I had been forgotten. I don’t want to sound like I’m attacking anyone but after a few months without anyone checking in, I felt the way I did the last time something terrible happened, like I had been abandoned. I don’t know what else I was supposed to expect really, I haven’t built close relationships with anyone new for a long time, partly because the circumstances have meant that I don’t keep in touch or because I struggle mentally with interacting when I don’t see people very often. Perhaps I have idealised my (apparently) longer lasting friendships too much. Perhaps the sands of time laid waste to these relationships and I hadn’t seen it.</p>
        <p>What would have been nice though, is to have had an inkling that this might have been the case. It’s bewildering to realise that the people you have valorised no longer hold you in the same level of esteem. It’s dumbfounding to realise that you haven’t moved on when they have. It’s traumatic to think that perhaps it had always been this way.</p>
        <p>I meant to write this last year, but the last paragraph was too difficult to articulate until now. Especially in the context of knowing I have very limited outlets for expression and reciprocation, I have a couple of people who I can talk to and I am very grateful for that. I hope this doesn’t sound like hyperbole. I don’t want to cause friction and neither do I want to hurt anyone else, but the truth is that because I don’t value myself, I don’t have plans, I don’t have dreams and I don’t look to the future.</p>  
        > </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 17:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/therapy?.html</guid>
    </item>

        <item>
        <title>Critiquing Ideology. Challenging Rules.</title>
        <link>https://www.wamsicks.uk/cicr.html</link>
        <description><
        <h1>Critiquing Ideology. Challenging Rules.</h1>
        <h3>My first proper post. Don't say I didn't warn you.</h3>
        <h3>First published: 1st March 2019</h3>
        <p>When I first read Gramsci’s work, I didn’t really get it. The translation that I read was old and written with an academic tone that almost said “you have to be one of us to understand”. I proceeded to try again and again until it began to fall into place. With many emancipatory understandings, you expect a euphoria, or the feeling that some shackles have been loosened, or most commonly that it would be like a blindfold had finally been ripped away and you were finally able to see the light. The truth was more terrifying. If anyone has seen the film, <em>They Live </em>by John Carpenter starring Rowdy Roddy Piper, they’ll understand what I mean when I say it’s the opposite. This film is one of the most obvious displays of how ideology works. John Nada finds a pair of sunglasses and when he puts them on, he sees things for what they really are.</p>
        <p>Hegemonic ideology is the foundation of our understanding of life and what we see around us and affects our every action and reaction. An example is when someone does work for a family member and even though may have been simple, easy and may not have actually cost anything, there is an insistence from the family member who needed help to offer money as recompense. In this situation, the person who helped will insist as fervently that they will not take any money as it was simple and they were doing it as a kindness. The two family members are essentially playing a game to see how nice they are. Another example is when someone offers the last of something, the implication is that everyone else refuse so that they can enjoy it, although not everyone falls for this ploy of being nice.</p>
        <p>These are quite small examples and they show us exactly how it permeates throughout our daily lives, but it works on a huge level as <em>They Live </em>shows us. This cultural supremacy, is not the result of coercion. This is a fundamental problem for those who view hegemony in terms of a struggle, particularly those who view it from a class struggle standpoint. The continuance of ideology is based on consent. This is not the same as saying that people want to view the world this way or that they even understand what is going on but it requires that people do not challenge it and accept its rules and the regulation of daily life implicitly. This is not to say that every ideology is the same, or even that it is constant. It is very much an open-ended phenomenon, else it would not have been able to develop from what had gone before and would not be able to develop into something else.</p>
        <p>Ideology in this sense is a cultural hegemony and can therefore can affect different nations, socioeconomic groups and even family relations. One of my lecturers once said that he went to his wife’s parents for Christmas and they brought out the tin of chocolates to share. He took a handful and immediately saw the looks on the faces of his parents-in-law. This was a faux pas whereas in his own family this would have been completely normal. Of course, this is comparing apples and pears when looking at this example and perhaps white supremacy but it follows that there are unwritten rules that we do not challenge. But, and admittedly this is only my inference, there is an acceptance here that whilst you were offered an abundance, you should submit to frugality. This of course is not the same as the ideology of the KKK, who although they told themselves and each other that they were the purest Christian fundamentalists and therefore good, giving and charitable, whilst killing black men and raping black women. Wait a fucking minute, how does that work?</p>
        <p>Cultural hegemony is not just how you follow the rules, it is also about how you break them. If I was going out drinking as a teenager or a young adult, my parents would have been ok with this and would have accepted this as a part of growing up. However, if I were to ever do this in front of them then I would be punished. But it goes the other way too, those who follow the rules too well can also be punished. Slavoj Žižek uses the example of Stalin giving a speech and then opening a public debate of what he had said. The first person stands up and criticises Stalin and what he had to say. We all know that his friends would be asking who saw him last the morning after. A second person interjects and confronts him stating that no one can talk about comrade Stalin in that manner. He would have been even luckier to wake up in the morning.</p>
        <p>So, what do we do about this? The problem is to avoid cynicism and find a way of piecing together an understanding of the world whilst repelling the unseen hand of ideology. Like the fight scene in <em>They Live</em>, you can’t always make others understand the way that you do. It is important though to look around and get accustomed to seeking out these unwritten rules that govern things and challenge their supremacy and often their idiocy. It needs to be looked at, understood and challenged over and over again before it really starts to make sense. How does it affect you? Discovering how it really comes into your life is the best way of coming to terms with it.</p>  
        > </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 17:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://www.wamsicks.uk/cicr.html</guid>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>